Guide to the Dwight Le Merton Bolinger Papers SC0473
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Dwight Le Merton Bolinger papers
1933-1993
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Bolinger, Dwight Le Merton
SC0473
61.75 Linear Feet
Papers include correspondence, class materials, drafts of articles, published works, audio tapes, and reference files including many card files.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Gift of the estate of Dwight Bolinger, 1992, and of Bruce Bolinger, 1995.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Dwight L. Bolinger, English linguistic expert and scholar of the Spanish language, was a visiting professor at Stanford University from 1978 until his death in 1992. He earned his AB at Washburn College in 1930, his MA at the University of Kansas in 1932, and his Ph.D. at the University of Wisconsin in 1936. Before coming to Stanford, he taught at Washburn College, University of Southern California (1944-1960), University of Colorado, and Harvard University (1963-1973). He was the author of 17 books and over three hundred articles.
Description of the Collection
Papers include correspondence, class materials, drafts of articles, published works, audio tapes, and reference files including many card files.
Phonotapes.; Intonation (Phonetics).; Language and languages.; Linguistics.; Bolinger, Dwight Le Merton; Bolinger, Dwight Le Merton
- Papers, Accession ARCH-1992-101
  - Professional correspondence: A – Boyd (Box 1)
  - Bradley [all] (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Brazil [all] (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Breivik, L. E., 1976-78 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Brennan, Susan, 1988-89 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Brett, Lewis E., 1953-61 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Brewer [all] (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Bright, William, 1970-86 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Britannica, Encyclopaedia, 1933-87 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Broeders, Ton, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Bronstein, Arthur, 1964-91 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Brooks [all] (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Brown University, 1974-76 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Brown(e) [all] (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Brugman, Claudia, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Bugarski, Ranko, 1966-69 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Burchfield, Robert, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Burton-Roberts, Noel, 1974-80 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Bush [all] (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Butters, Ronald R., 1977-82 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Buzhor, Yuri, 1983, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Calderon, Alvaro, 1987-91 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Calgary, University of, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - California, University of [assorted campuses], 1975-79 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Cambridge University Press, 1972-90 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Canada Council, 1968-90 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Canadian Journal of Linguistics, H.B. Smeaton, 1953-69 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Canada – all other (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Cancino, Herlinda, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Canfield, D. Lincoln, 1952-68 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Cannon, Garland, 1960-87 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Cantrall, William R., 1971-77 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Carden, Guy, 1982-83 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Carlson [all] (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Carnegie (assorted foundations) (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Caro y Cuervo (institute in Bogota, Colombia), 1946-87 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Carpenter, Kathie, 1982-83 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Carroll [all] (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Carter, Hazel, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Casa, Frank P., 1968-80 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Caso, Adolph, 1971, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Cassidy, Frederic G., 1948-75 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Castaneda, James A., 1959-1990 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Castilla, Alberto, 1974-75 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Catford, J. C., 1985 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Center for Applied Linguistics, 1959-80 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Cessaris, Ann C., 1982-90 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Chandola, Anoop C., 1976-78 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Chafe, Wallace L. 1971-88 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Chang-Rodriguez, Eugenio, 1950-76 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Charnley, M. Bertens, 1952-73 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - de Chasca, Edmund, 1944-68 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Chatman, Seymour, 1956-63 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Chatterjee, Ranjit, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Chicago Linguistic Society, 1978-82 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Chicago, University of, 1969-72 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Chisholm, William S., 1971-86 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Chomsky, Noam, 1960-87 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Chvany, Catherine V., 1971-92 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Cintas, Pierre, 1962-86 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Clark(e) [all] (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Clark University, 1964-68 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Cohen [all] (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Colarusso, John, 1979-84 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - College Composition and Communication, 1957-58 (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - College English, 1938-57 (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Collier [all] (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Collins [all] (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - Colodny, I., 1937-84 (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - Colorado [all] (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - Columbia [all] (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - Comrie, Bernard, 1977-78 (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - Contreras, Heles and Lidia, 1959-80 (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - Cook(e) [all] (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - Cooper [all] (Box 2, Folder 74)
  - Copeland, James E., 1980-91 (Box 2, Folder 75)
  - Cormier, Ray, 1966-82 (Box 2, Folder 76)
  - Cornell University (Box 2, Folder 77)
  - de Cornulier, Benoit, 1974-87 (Box 2, Folder 78)
  - Corominas, John, 1953, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 79)
  - Coseriu, Eugenio, 1967-86 (Box 2, Folder 80)
  - Coto, Luis & Herminia, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 81)
  - Cotter, Colleen, 1989-91 (Box 2, Folder 82)
  - Coulmas, Florian, 1979-86 (Box 2, Folder 83)
  - Cowan, J. Milton, 1948-78 (Box 2, Folder 84)
  - Craddock, Jerry R., 1961-73 (Box 2, Folder 85)
  - Creider, Chet, 1977-78 (Box 2, Folder 86)
  - Crespi, Bob, 1969=89 (Box 2, Folder 87)
  - Crocker [all] (Box 2, Folder 88)
  - Croft, Bill, 1988-91 (Box 2, Folder 89)
  - Cruttenden, Alan, 1976-91 (Box 2, Folder 90)
  - Crystal, David, 1970-86 (Box 2, Folder 91)
  - Culicover, Peter W., 1981 (Box 2, Folder 92)
  - Cuthbertson, Stuart, 1943-49 (Box 2, Folder 93)
  - Cutler, Preston S., 1979-89 (Box 2, Folder 94)
  - Professional correspondence: Dahbany – Funk (Box 3)
  - Professional correspondence: Gabrosek – Helzron (Box 4)
  - Professional correspondence: Hewson – Key (Box 5)
  - Professional correspondence: King – Malecot (Box 6)
  - Professional correspondence: Malkiel - Pellowe (Box 7)
  - Professional correspondence: Penfield – Sharp (detailed list follows) (Box 8)
  - Penfield, Joyce, 1984-87 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Peng, Fred C. C., 1976-79 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Penhallurick, John M., 1982-83 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Penzl, Herbert, 1979-80 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Perez [all] (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Pergamon Press, 1988-91 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Pergnier, Maurice, 1986-89 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Perlmutter, David M., 1968-84 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Perry [all] (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Peters, Robert A., 1964-80 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Peters [all others] (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Pettersson, Thore, 1984 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Pharies, David, 1978-88 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Phillips [all] (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Pierrehumbert, Janet B., 1980-81 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Pike, Kenneth L., 1948-89 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Pocheptsov, Georgi G., 1967-72 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Preziosi, Donald, 1976-78, 1976-72 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Pride, John B., 1980-85 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Prince [all – mostly Ellen F. Prince] (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Pulgram, Ernst, 1958-89 (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - Pullin, Bill, 1977 [only outgoing to] (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - Pullum, Geoff, 1980, 1991 (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - Quirk, Randolph, 1961-69 (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - Quirk, Randolph, 1970 (Box 8, Folder 25)
  - Quirk, Randolph, 1971-1990 (Box 8, Folder 26)
  - Rabanales, Ambrosio, 1953-79 (Box 8, Folder 27)
  - Ransom, Evelyn, 1979-84 (Box 8, Folder 28)
  - Rameh, Clea, 1984 (Box 8, Folder 29)
  - Rea, John A., 1956-80 (Box 8, Folder 30)
  - Read, Allen Walker, 1941-89 (Box 8, Folder 31)
  - Redenbarger, Wayne, 1972-74 (Box 8, Folder 32)
  - Redfern, James G., 1971-81 (Box 8, Folder 33)
  - Reich, Peter A., 1976-79 (Box 8, Folder 34)
  - Reid / Reed [all] (Box 8, Folder 35)
  - Reyes, Rogelio, 1973-89 (Box 8, Folder 36)
  - Rhymes, Barbara C., 1985 (Box 8, Folder 37)
  - Ricci, Julio [in Spanish], 1963-87 (Box 8, Folder 38)
  - Rickford, John R., 1981-85 (Box 8, Folder 39)
  - Riddle [all] (Box 8, Folder 40)
  - Ritchie, William C., 1973-74 (Box 8, Folder 41)
  - Rivers [all – mostly Wilga Rivers] (Box 8, Folder 42)
  - Rodman, Robert, 1976-77 (Box 8, Folder 43)
  - Rodriguez / Rodrigues [all] (Box 8, Folder 44)
  - Rogers [all] (Box 8, Folder 45)
  - Ronat, Mitsou, 1984 (Box 8, Folder 46)
  - Rosen [all] (Box 8, Folder 47)
  - Rosenberg [all] (Box 8, Folder 48)
  - Ross, John Robert (Haj), 1966-1991 (Box 8, Folder 49)
  - Ruhl, Charles, 1976-88 (Box 8, Folder 50)
  - Russell, I. Willis, 1942-82 (Box 8, Folder 51)
  - Rutherford [all] (Box 8, Folder 52)
  - Ruwet, Nicolas, 1981-83 (Box 8, Folder 53)
  - Ryan [all] (Box 8, Folder 54)
  - Sackett [all] (Box 8, Folder 55)
  - Sacks, Norman P., 1956-91 (Box 8, Folder 56)
  - Safire, William (letters to), 1981-90 (Box 8, Folder 57)
  - Sag, Ivan, 1975-90 (Box 8, Folder 58)
  - St. Clair, Robert, 1973-79 (Box 8, Folder 59)
  - Salkoff, Morris, 1983-86 (Box 8, Folder 60)
  - Saltarelli, Mario, 1975-84 (Box 8, Folder 61)
  - Salus, Peter, 1978-86 (Box 8, Folder 62)
  - San Francisco Chronicle; San Francisco State U. (Box 8, Folder 63)
  - Saporta, Sol, 1954-72 (Box 8, Folder 64)
  - Schachter, Paul, 1959-73 (Box 8, Folder 65)
  - Scherer, Klaus R., 1971-88 (Box 8, Folder 66)
  - Schlesinger, I. M., 1973-86 (Box 8, Folder 67)
  - Schmerling, Susan F., 1972-82 (Box 8, Folder 68)
  - Schubiger, Maria, 1952-80 (Box 8, Folder 69)
  - Schwartz [all – mostly Kessel and Arthur] (Box 8, Folder 70)
  - Scott [all] 1944-75 (Box 8, Folder 71)
  - Scur, G. S., 1965-75 (Box 8, Folder 72)
  - Sebeok, Thomas A., 1954-82 (Box 8, Folder 73)
  - Segreda, Memo, 1964-71 (Box 8, Folder 74)
  - Seiler, H., 1981-84 (Box 8, Folder 75)
  - Sereno, Joan, 1986 (Box 8, Folder 76)
  - Shakhbagova, Juliette, 1972-90 (Box 8, Folder 77)
  - Shapiro, Barbara and Shapiro, Norman R., 1986-87 (Box 8, Folder 78)
  - Sharp, Alan E., 1962-63 (Box 8, Folder 79)
  - Professional correspondence: Shen – Winograd (Box 9)
  - Professional correspondence: Winter – Zwicky (Box 10a)
  - Older correspondence: Abe – Farsi (Box 10b)
  - Older correspondence: Fish – Moreno (Box 11)
  - Older correspondence: Navarro – Wise (detailed list follows) (Box 12)
  - Navarro, Tomas, 1952-84 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Navas Ruiz, Ricardo, 1963-70 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Nehring, Alfons, 1948-64 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Nelson [all] (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Noss, Richard B., 1973-78 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Nostrand, Howard Lee, 1951-63 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Olmsted, David L., 1954-61 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - de Onis, Jose, 1960-65 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Osma, Jose-Maria, 1939-86 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Padron, Alfredo F. (in Spanish), 1951-64 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Poldauf, Ivan, 1954-84 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Poston, Lawrence, Jr., 1953-75 (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Reid, J. Richard, 1947-68 (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Reiss, Samuel, 1953 (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - Roberts, Paul, 1963-64 (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - Roeming, Robert F., 1967-70 (Box 12, Folder 16)
  - Roldan [all, mostly Mercedes Roldan] (Box 12, Folder 17)
  - Rona, Jose Pedro, 1963-74 (Box 12, Folder 18)
  - Saenz, Hilario, 1953-63 (Box 12, Folder 19)
  - Sanchez, Jose (Pepe), 1949-66 (Box 12, Folder 20)
  - Sandmann, M., 1956-60 (Box 12, Folder 21)
  - Santos, Maria Quinzon, 1955-62 (Box 12, Folder 22)
  - Sapon, Stanley M., 1954-65 (Box 12, Folder 23)
  - Sedwick, Frank, 1951-68 (Box 12, Folder 24)
  - Sewell, Ernestine P, 1978-80 (Box 12, Folder 25)
  - Shen, Yao, 1960-64 (Box 12, Folder 26)
  - Shoemaker, W. H., 1939-63 (Box 12, Folder 27)
  - Siegel, Richard, 1963-69 (Box 12, Folder 28)
  - Sik, Andrew E., 1951-52 (Box 12, Folder 29)
  - Smith, Henry Lee, Jr., 1956-73 (Box 12, Folder 30)
  - Solano, Louis, 1968-69 (Box 12, Folder 31)
  - Sparkman, Colley F., 1948-72 (Box 12, Folder 32)
  - Spitzer, Leo, 1945-54 (Box 12, Folder 33)
  - Staubach, Charles N., 1955-68 (Box 12, Folder 34)
  - Stetson, R. H., 1945-49 (Box 12, Folder 35)
  - Swett, Douglas B., 1948-55 (Box 12, Folder 36)
  - Symposium (journal), 1946-48 (Box 12, Folder 37)
  - Tamony, Peter, 1937-83 (Box 12, Folder 38)
  - Toronto, University of, and Pierre Leon, 1969-70 (Box 12, Folder 39)
  - Trager, George L., 1945-77 (Box 12, Folder 40)
  - Trevino, S.N., 1943-62 (Box 12, Folder 41)
  - Twadell, W. F., 1953-76 (Box 12, Folder 42)
  - Vazquez Bigi, A. Manuel, 1960-68 (Box 12, Folder 43)
  - Venter, Jan A., 1958-59 (Box 12, Folder 44)
  - de Vila, Maria Arsuaga, 1962-69 (Box 12, Folder 45)
  - Wade, Gerald E., 1954-60 (Box 12, Folder 46)
  - Walsh, Donald D., 1949-60 (Box 12, Folder 47)
  - Walsh, Donald D., 1961-62 (Box 12, Folder 48)
  - Walsh, Donald D., 1963-80 (Box 12, Folder 49)
  - Weinreich, Uriel, 1955-64 (Box 12, Folder 50)
  - Whitney, Willis R., 1953-55 (Box 12, Folder 51)
  - Williams, Edwin B., 1950-73 (Box 12, Folder 52)
  - Wimsatt, W. K., Jr., 1954-65 (Box 12, Folder 53)
  - Wise, G. M, 1944-63 (Box 12, Folder 54)
  - Class materials – include USC material (Box 13)
  - Hashin (Box 14)
  - Spanish grammar material (Box 14)
  - English "overflow" (Box 14)
  - Miscellaneous files (garage) (Box 15)
  - Works in progress (Box 16)
  - Works in progress (Box 17)
  - Unpublished articles (Box 18)
  - Unpublished articles (Box 19)
  - Published articles (Box 19)
  - Published articles (Box 20)
  - Published articles (Box 21)
  - Published articles (publications – general) (Box 22)
  - Talks (Box 22)
  - Talks (Box 23)
  - Material related to published work – galleys, etc. (Box 23)
  - Essays on Spanish – galleys (Box 24)
  - Hum 109 problems/handouts (Box 24)
  - Intonation and Its Uses (Box 24)
  - Inton(ation) and its parts (Box 25)
  - Drafts of other work (Box 25)
  - Drafts of work published (Box 26)
  - Material on smoking bans (Box 26)
  - Miscellaneous card file groupings (Box 26)
  - Card files (Box 27)
  - "Magazines" used in study (Box 27)
  - Card files (Box 28)
  - Miscellaneous material used in study (Box 29)
  - Notebooks (Box 29)
  - Long card file box (Box 30)
  - Long card file box (Box 31)
  - Class notes (?) (Box 32)
  - Class notes (Box 33)
  - Misc. correspondence A – Fr/G (Box 34)
- Additional Papers, Accession ARCH-1995-009
  - Correspondence: A -D (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: F -G (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: Ha (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: He -Hu (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence: 1-J (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: Ka -Kn (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: Ko -Ku (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: L (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: Ma -Me (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence: Me -Mu (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence: N -0 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence: P (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence: Q -Ri (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence: Ro -Sc (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence: Se -Sz (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence: T (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence: U-Z (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Bibliographic page (fragment) (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Comments on the pitch accent, MLA, December 1989 (t.s.) (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Indicative and subjunctive, 1971 (t.s. article) (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - L.A. linguistics circle, November 1957 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Obituary and bibliography, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Reprints (Bolinger) (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Reprints (Bolinger) (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Visual side of language (talk) (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Audiovisual material
    - Belfast Intonation 1 (Jarman), 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 3)
    - Bolinger, Intonation and its parts, 1985, 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 3)
    - Bolinger, Nondeclaratives, Chicago, April 1982, 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 3)
    - Bolinger, Power to the utterance, 1987, 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 3)
    - Brazil, Coulthard, Johns: Discourse intonation, 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 3)
    - Cavett show, September 1978, 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 3)
    - Finley, Art & Dan Travanti, radio pronunciation, 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 3)
    - Itonama intonation, 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 3)
    - Network tone of voice, 1981, 1-4 ( 4 tapes), 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 3)
    - Nunberg, Geoff: Language pieces, 1989-91 (from "Fresh Air"), 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 3)
    - Reagan on Lebanon bombing, 1983, 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 3)
    - Sea of Languages: Western Public Radio, 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 3)
    - Shopen, Williams - English dialects, 1980 (accomp. to book), 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 3)
    - Speech tune test 1981, 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 3)
    - Van Lancker, Diana: Idiom, 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 3)
    - Javanese intonation, 1 audiotape(s) (Reel-to-Reel) (Box 3)
- Additional Papers, Accession ARCH-2018-016
  - Correspondence, 1941-1945 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Reprints, 1969-1989 (Box 1, Folder 2)